<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Bishops Courts dissolved, or, The law of England touching ecclesiastical jurisdiction stated wherein it appears that the spiritual courts want both power and might to execute their wills upon his Majesties good subjects at his day : being a short and brief account of the several statutes made concerning the spiritual and ecclesiastical jurisdiction / by E.W.</title>
            <author>Whitaker, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186469</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11983671</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11983671</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51917</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65678)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51917)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 523:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Bishops Courts dissolved, or, The law of England touching ecclesiastical jurisdiction stated wherein it appears that the spiritual courts want both power and might to execute their wills upon his Majesties good subjects at his day : being a short and brief account of the several statutes made concerning the spiritual and ecclesiastical jurisdiction / by E.W.</title>
                  <author>Whitaker, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36, 32-35 [i.e. 40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Reyner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51917:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51917:1"/>
            <p>THE Biſhops Courts DISSOLVED: OR, THE LAW OF ENGLAND TOUCHING Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction STATED.</p>
            <p>Wherein it appears that the Spiritual Courts want both Power and Might to execute their Wills upon his Majeſties good Subjects at this day.</p>
            <p>BEING A ſhort and brief Account of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Statutes made concerning the Spiritual and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>By E. W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Reyner,</hi> to be ſold by <hi>Rich. Janeway</hi> in <hi>Queens-head-alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-noſter-row.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51917:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51917:2"/>
            <head>THE Biſhops Courts DISSOLVED: OR, THE Law of England Touching Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction Stated.</head>
            <p>THe deſign of this Narrative, whatever Cenſurers it may meet with, hath no other end than to bring truth to light, and that truth more eſpecially which hath been ſo long maſqued and hid under Church-mens Gowns; and which hath been moſt induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly concealed with great Artifice from the ignorant vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, as they are generally pleaſed to term Lay-men; though ſome of thoſe Lay men, nay, the moſt of them, I think, are both for Parts and Piety not in the leaſt inferiour to the beſt of them, though they call themſelves the only Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as if every member of Chriſts Church were not the Clergy or Gods heritage as well as they.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:51917:3"/>
            <p>But my preſent buſineſs is only to meddle with the coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive power they pretend to in Courts Chriſtian, or Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Juriſdiction, which for them to claim ſuch a power in <hi>England</hi> diſtinct from the legal power known in this Kingdom, and contrary to the Supremacy of the King, in direct oppoſition to his Authority, as he is by Law ſupreme head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is a very great wonder to me, and I believe to the Ingenuous Reader, if he conſider the matter of fact as it lyes.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, the Reader muſt know that all manner of Spiritual Juriſdiction uſed in this Nation had its original and foundation from the un-holy Mother Church, the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Canon Law: and was born or rather brought into this Northern Iſland of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk: for before his time we do not find any tract of Church-Government (that is) by way of Excommunication in Court Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>When he came here it was with the ſame ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that <hi>Rome</hi> and her Adherents and Devotaries to this day uſe, that is, decency and regular government of the Church of Chriſt: But no ſooner had this Monk ſet foot into this Kingdome but he began to ſhew his cloven foot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as it evidently appear'd in a very ſhort time after, for when he found that the Chriſtians in this Iſland were more holy than himſelf; and that they liked not his Pride and Arrogancy, he fell upon the Monks of <hi>Bangor,</hi> and began to Curſe them with Bell, Book, and Candle, till they ſhould ſubmit to him and the unholy See of <hi>Rome.</hi> And from that time, and not before, all manner of Eccleſiaſtical Courts and Cenſures of the Church both grew and continued in this Kingdom (until the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Popes Authority: and how they uſed the people in theſe Courts, and how many were murdered and deſtroyed for Religion ſake in all that time, is too great a number now to be reckoned.</p>
            <p>But not withſtanding they had this vaſt power, and held Courts Canonical (as they term them) by Authority from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> even from <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk, to <hi>William</hi> the Firſt (commonly called the Conquerour) and from thence to the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, yet the Biſhops and Clergy of <hi>England</hi> ſometimes by the Statute Law of the Land met with many rubs in their Canon Law: for their oppreſſions being become very great, even ſo great that in thoſe dark times and fogs of Popery the Lay-men began to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51917:3"/>diſcover their cheats, and therefore the wings of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy began ſometimes to be a little clipped by the Statute Law of the Land, as you will find by ſeveral Statutes made ſince <hi>Henry</hi> the Third:<note place="margin">Vide Rot. An. <hi>1257. 3</hi> Ed. primi Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> particularly in the Statute made in <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt's time, which ordains, That a Clerk being indicted of Felony by ſolemn Inqueſt of lawful men in the Kings Court, in no manner ſhall be delivered without due Purgation.</p>
            <p>Now before this Statute the Church-men pleaded exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption from the Temporal Law; and offenders, it ſhould ſeem, which were Church-men claimed a priviledge to be only lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the power of the Church.</p>
            <p>In the next place you will find by the Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt in the thirteenth year of his Reign the Spiritual Courts were preſcribed what it was they ſhould be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to take Cognizance of and no more, ſee the Statute, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>The King to his Iudges ſendeth gréeting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Called</hi> Stat. de circumſpect. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatis <hi>made 13</hi> E. <hi>1.</hi> Anno Dom. <hi>1285.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vſe your ſelves circumſpectly in all matters concerning the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Norwich <hi>and his Clergy, not puniſhing them if they hold plea in Court Chriſtian of ſuch things as be meer Spiritual, that is, to wit, of Penances enjoyned by Prelates for deadly ſins, as Fornication, Adultery, and ſuch like, for the which ſometimes corporal Penance, and ſometimes pecuniary is enjoyned, eſpecially if a Frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be convicted of ſuch things.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Now after this Kings time thoſe ſpiritual men finding themſelves by his Laws kept within ſome moderate bounds,<note place="margin">Vid. Rot. de Artic. Cleri An. <hi>9</hi> Ed. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; A. D. <hi>1315.</hi>
               </note> grew very uneaſie; and therefore in <hi>Edward</hi> the Second's time they began to ſtir for the enlarging their power: For you will find in his Reign that the Clergy got Laws to paſs then, that the Clergy might correct in their Spiritual Courts for defamation, and corporal penance was to be enjoyned, as you may ſee by the Rolls of thoſe times.</p>
            <p>In theſe Statutes made at <hi>Lincoln</hi> they had diverſe Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges given them,<note place="margin">Idem Cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as in the third Chapter they had power allowed them to lay Corporal puniſhment.</p>
            <p>And in the fourth Chapter,<note place="margin">Cap, <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Prelates might correct for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation by that Statute.</p>
            <p>In the eighth Chapter it appears that the Clergy did uſe to meddle with the Kings ſervants,<note place="margin">Idem Cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> and cenſure them at their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51917:4"/>pleaſure, till they were limited and bounded by this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: which Ordinance, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>It pleaſed our Lord the King that ſuch Clerks that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in his ſervice, if they oſtend they ſhall be corrected by their Ordinary, like as other, but ſo long as they are occupied about the Exchequer, they ſhall not be bound to kéep Reſidence in their Churches.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And in the ſame year among the Articles made for to give power,<note place="margin">Idem Cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> and to reſtrain: it is ordained, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Alſo if any dignity be vacant, where Election is to be made, it is moved that the Electors may fréely make their Election without fear of any power Temporal.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The Kings Anſwer was, <q>They ſhall be made frée accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the form of Statutes and Ordinances.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This power continued to the Clergy till King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, only ſometimes there was ſome ſmall abridgements by ſeveral Statutes and Ordinances, as in 31 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. where their Extortion about Fees was by the Statute regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.<note place="margin">Vide Rot. <hi>31</hi> Ed. <hi>3.</hi> Cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing wherein the wings of the Clergy were clipped, was by the Statute of 16 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. which declares purchaſing Bulls from the See of <hi>Rome</hi> unlawful, and a Premunire ſo to do:<note place="margin">Vide <hi>16</hi> Rich. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and ordains among diverſe other things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Whereupon our Lord the King by the aſſent aforeſaid, and at the requeſt of the ſaid Commons hath ordained and eſtabliſhed that if any purchaſe or purſue or cauſe to be purchaſed or purſued in the Court of</hi> Rome <hi>or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, by any ſuch Tranſlations, Proceſſes or Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Excommunications, Bulls, Inſtruments, or any other things whatſoever, which touch the King, againſt him, his Crown, or his Regality, or his Realm, as is aforeſaid, and they which bring within the Realm, or them receive, or make thereof Notification, or any other Execution whatſoever, within the ſame Realm or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that they, their Notaries, Procurators, Maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Abettors, Factors, and Councellors, ſhall be put out of the Kings protection,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſhall forfeit all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51917:4"/>their Lands and Tenements, Goods and Chattels, and make Ranſome to the King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that proceſs be made againſt them by</hi> praemunire facias, <hi>in manner as it is ordained in other Statures of Proviſoes and others, which do ſue in any other Court, in derogation of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality of our Lord the King.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>In <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's time we find the Clergy prayed Aid of the Common Law,<note place="margin">Vide H. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> to help them to puniſh their Prieſts and Clerks for Incontinency.</p>
            <p>Which Statute gives the Biſhops power to puniſh ſuch offender by their Epiſcopal Juriſdiction, as was to them thought moſt meet, and to be freed from any action to be brought againſt them for the ſame at Law.</p>
            <p>Thus they continued without any Interruption until the fatal time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and even in his time till the twenty firſt we do not find any great adding or diminiſhing from them or the power they pretended to by their Canon Law, for it muſt be obſerved, and it will not be denyed by any perſon, but that ſtill the power the Clergy of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> ever had, except what was given them by Statute Law, was only the Canon Law brought with them from their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy Mother, the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In 21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.<note place="margin">Stat. <hi>21</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Spiritual perſons are abridged from having pluralities of Livings, and from taking of Farms, or to deal in Merchandize, and that all Diſpenſations contrary to this Statute ſhall be void, by which it ſeems the Clergy were Merchants for Temporals as well as Spiritual before that time.</p>
            <p>In 23 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.<note place="margin">23 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> another Act was made which reaches their Court more eſpecially than any before that time, called, <hi>viz.</hi> (the Bill of <hi>Citetias</hi>) in which Law the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops are enjoyned not to cite any perſon out of their own Dioceſs where they live under a ſevere penalty, except it be for Hereſie and Probates of Wills, in which Law is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded 10 <hi>l.</hi> damages, beſides coſt to be recovered by the party grieved by action or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>6</label> In the ſame Act, <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. this very clauſe alſo is contained, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>And be it enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that no Arch-Biſhop or Biſhop, Ordinary, Official, Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or any other Subſtitute or Miniſter of the ſaid Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Arch-Deacons, or others having
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51917:5"/>Spiritual Iuriſdiction, at any time from the Feaſt of</hi> Eaſter <hi>next coming, ſhall ask, demand, take or receive of any of the Kings Subjects any ſumm or ſumms of money for the Seal o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any Citation afer the ſaid Feaſt, to be awarded or obtained, then only</hi> 3 d. <hi>Sterling, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the pains and penalties afore limited, contained and expreſſed in this preſent Act to be in like form recovered, as is aforeſaid.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>But now though this Law is ſo plain as nothing can be made more plain, yet to this day their Spiritual Courts Conſcience are large enough to take inſtead of 3 <hi>d.</hi> for every Sealed Citation not leſs than 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> or ſuch like ſumm, to the ſhame and reproach not only to themſelves, but even to the whole Nation that ſuffers ſuch abuſes to be put upon the people contrary to all Law, and when remedy may eaſily be had.</p>
            <p>In 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> Another Act was made, which takes away all Appeals to the See of <hi>Rome:</hi> and becauſe it may moſt evidently appear that the Spiritual and Temporal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction was ever a Flower to the Imperial Crown of this Realm, I ſhall here inſert <hi>in haec verba</hi> part of the ſecond Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that Statute, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>And whereas the King and his moſt noble Progenitors, and the Nobility and Commons of this Realm, at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and ſundry Parliaments, as well in the time of King</hi> Edward <hi>the Firſt,</hi> Edward <hi>the Third,</hi> Richard <hi>the Second,</hi> Henry <hi>the Fourth, and other Noble Kings of this Realm, made ſundry Ordinances, Laws, Statutes and Proviſions, for the entire and ſure conſervation of the prerogatives, liberties and preheminencies of the ſaid Imperial Crown of this Realm, and of the Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions Spiritual and Temporal of the ſame, to keep it from the Annoyance as well of the Sée of</hi> Rome, <hi>as from the Authority of other foreign Potentates attempting the diminution or violation thereof, as often and from time to time, as any ſuch annoyance or attempt might be known or eſpied, and notwithſtanding the ſaid good Statutes and Ordinances made in the time of the Kings moſt noble Progenitors, in preſervation of the Authority and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of the ſaid Imperial Crown as is aforeſaid,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51917:5"/>
            <p>By which recital in this Statute it is moſt plain, that all Spiritual Juriſdiction is and ought to be derived from and under the Prerogative of the King and the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> as will more fully appear by the remaining part of the Statute, too long here to be inſerted.</p>
            <p>But now in 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.<note place="margin">25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> the whole power of the Clergy, and all their Authority is acknowledged to be in the King, and all Canons to ceaſe, and they never to make more but by Commiſſions from and under him, by virtue of that Act entituled, <hi>viz.</hi> The Submiſſion of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and reſtraint of Appeals: Which begins thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Whereas the Kings humble and obedient Subiects the Clergy of the Realm of</hi> England <hi>have not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged according to truth, that the Convocations of the ſame Clergy is, always hath béen, and ought to be aſſembled only by the Kings Writ, but alſo ſubmitting themſelves to the Kings Majeſty, have promiſed</hi> (In verb Sacerdotii) <hi>that they will never from henceforth preſume to attempt, alledge, claim, or put in ure, enact, promulge, or execute any new Canons, Conſtitutions, Ordinances, Provincial or others, or by whatſoever name they ſhall be called in the Convocation, unleſs the Kings moſt Royal aſſent and licente may to them be had, to make, promulge, or execute the ſame. And that his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty do give his moſt Royal aſſent and authority in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. And whereas diverſe Conſtitutions, Ordinances and Canons, Provincial or Synodal, which heretofore have been enacted and be thought not only to be much prejudicial to the Kings Prerogative Royal, and repugnant to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, but alſo overmuch onerous to his Higneſs and his Subjects. The ſaid Clergy have moſt humbly beſought his Highneſs that the ſaid Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and Canons may be committed to the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Iudgement of his Highneſs, and of thirty two perſons of the Kings Subjects, whereof ſixteen to be of the upper and nether houſe of Parliament of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porality, and the other ſixtéen to be of the Clergy of this Realm, and all of the ſaid thirty two perſons to be choſen and appointed by his Majeſty,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51917:6"/>
            <p>And then Enacts, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority of this preſent Parliament, according to the ſaid ſubmiſſion and petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid Clergy that they nor either of them from henceforth ſhall preſume to attempt, alledge, claim, or put in urd any Conſtitutions or Ordinances, Provincial or Synodal, or any other Canons; nor ſhall enact, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulge, or execute any ſuch Canons, Conſtitutions or Ordinances Provincial, by whatſoever name or names they may be called in their convocations in time coming, which always ſhall be aſſembled by authority of the Kings Writ,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <p>And the Penalty for doing other than this Act directs was impriſonment, and Fine at the Kings will, as by the Statute more at large appears.</p>
            <p>So that by this Statute their whole power was now inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the King, and till new Canons were made, or the old ones confirmed, as the Statute directs, the Clergy of <hi>England</hi> could in no ſort act: and from that time of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Statute until this preſent, I cannot find that ever any liberty was given, or that any Canons were made or confirmed by Law, other than what were judged unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's time, and damn'd by Act of Parliament in 1640. Which you will hear more of by and by.</p>
            <p>If it be thus, then from 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. I muſt date their down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal, a moſt happy day to <hi>England</hi> from that time; and it may be ſaid, all their Canons are now out of doors, or at ſeaſt very lame: and if ſo, then let the Reader judge where is their Authority for their Courts, for they muſt and do own that it was the Canon Law they acted by; and if ſo, then ſure if they have no Canons to act by, or at beſt but doubtful Canons, then I conceive they can have no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er except they can find it by the Statute Law, which I would be glad to ſee.</p>
            <p>In the next place another Law is made againſt them in 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. which takes away all Firſt-fruits to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> and ordains that Elections of all Biſhops ſhall be by the Kings Writ under a ſevere pain.</p>
            <p>In the ſame year an Act is made to take away <hi>Peter-pence</hi> and Diſpenſations,<note place="margin">Idem cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> in which Statute it is expreſly declared
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51917:6"/>that this Land ought not to be ſubject or bound to any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws but ſuch as are of their own making within this Realm.</p>
            <p>The King being declared head of the Church,<note place="margin">26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly there enacted <hi>(viz.)</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Shall have full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from time to time to viſit, repreſs, redreſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, order, correct, reſtrain all ſuch errors, hereſies, abuſes, offences, contempts and enormities, whatſoever they be, which by any manner of Spiritual Authority or Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction ought or may lawfully be reformed, repreſſed, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, redreſſed, corrected, reſtrained or amended, moſt to the pleaſure of Almighty God,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This being the Caſe, what colour can here be for any Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or Eccleſiaſtical power to any perſon whatever, but what muſt be derived from and under the King, and by his Authority and Commiſſion, and in his name and not in their own, nor in the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the Reader may be more fully ſatisfied, I have here inſerted the Statute made 37 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.<note place="margin">37. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note> Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>viz.</hi> A Bill that the Doctors of Civil Law being mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried may exerciſe Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>In moſt humble wiſe ſhew and declare unto your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs your moſt faithful, humble and obedient Subjects, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons of this preſent Parliament aſſembled, That whereas your Royal Majeſtie is, and hath always been, juſtly by the word of God, Supreme head in the Earth in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and hath full power and authority to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, puniſh, and repreſs all manner of Hereſies, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Vires, Sins, Abuſes, Idolatries, Hypocriſies and Superſtitions, ſprung and growing within the ſame, and to exerciſe all other manner of Iuriſdictions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction: Nevertheleſs the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>and his adherents, minding utterly as much as in him lay, to aboliſh, obſcure and delete ſuch power given by God to the Princes of the Earth, whereby they might gether and get to themſelves the Government and rule of the world, have in their Councils and Synods Provincial, made, ordained, eſtabliſhed and decréed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Ordinances and Conſtitutions, that no Lay or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried man ſhould or might exerciſe or occupy any Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51917:7"/>Eccleſiaſtical, nor ſhould be any Iudge or Regiſter in any Court, commonly called Eccleſtatical Court, leſt their falſe and uſurped power, which they pretend, and went about to have in Chriſts Church ſhould decay, wax vile, and be of no reputation, as by the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Conſtitutions Provincial appeareth: Which ſtanding and remaining in their Effect, not aboliſhed by your Graces Laws, did ſound to appear to make greatly for the ſaid uſurped power of the ſaid Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>and to be directly replignant to your Majeſty as ſupreme head of the Church, and Prerogative Royal, your Grate being a Lay man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And albeit the ſaid Decrées, Ordinances and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by a Statute made in the five and twentieth year of your moſt noble reign, be utterly aboliſhed, fruſtrate, and of none effect: yet becauſe the contrary thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is not uſed, nor put in practice by the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Arch-Deacons, and other Eccleſiaſtical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have no manner of Iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical, but by, under, and from your Royal Majeſty, it addeth, or at the leaſt may give occaſion to ſome evil diſpoſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to think, and little to regard the procéedings and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures Eccleſiaſtical made by your Highneſs and your Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, Officials, Commiſſaries, Iudges and Viſitators, being alſo Lay and Married men, to be of little or none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or force, whereby the people gathereth heart and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to do evil, and not to have ſuch reverence to your moſt Godly injunctions and procéedings as becometh them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But foraſmuch as your Majeſty is the only and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſupreme head of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and alſo of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>to whom by Holy Scripture all authority and power is wholly given to hear and determine all manner of cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, and to correct all vice and ſin whatſoever; and to all ſuch perſons as your Majeſty ſhall appoint thereunto: That in conſideration thereof, as well for the Inſtruction of ignorant perſons, as alſo to avoid the occaſion of the opinion aforeſaid, and the ſetting forth of your prerogative Royal and Supremacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It may therefore pleaſe your Highneſs, that it may be ordained and enacted by the authority of this preſent Parliament, That all and ſingular perſons, as well Lay, as thoſe that be now married, or hereafter ſhall be married, being Doctors of the Civil Law, lawfully
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51917:7"/>create, and made in any Vniverſity which ſhall be made, ordained, conſtituted and deputed to be any Chancellour, Vicar-General, Commiſſary, Official, Scribe or Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, by your Majeſty or any of your Heirs or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or by any Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, Arch-Deacon, or other perſon whatſoever, having authority under your Majeſty, your Heirs and Succeſſors to make any Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, Vicar-General, Commiſſary. Offical or Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, may lawfully execute and exerciſe all manner of Iuriſdiction, commonly called Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction, and all Cenſures and Coercions appertaining or in any wiſe belonging unto the ſame, albe it ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be Lay, married or unmarried, ſo that they be Doctors of the Civil Law, as is aforeſaid; any Law, Conſtitution, or Ordinance, to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Now here it appears plain, that all Authority muſt be derived from the King, and he alone as head of this Church hath power to correct or amend Hereſies, and all other Miſdemeanours, having the ſole juriſdiction in Courts Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, called Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and none to be made, or Synold held, but by his authority and permiſſion, ſo that it cannot be imagined by any that the Clergy had power to make Canons either new, or to go on with their old ones, till another Law be made, and power given them by the King as the Law directs.</p>
            <p>And from this time of the making of this Law none of the Canons, or pretended Canons, are any more in force in <hi>England</hi> than if there never had been any ſuch thing in the world, This therefore I lay down as a ſure rule that the Eccleſiaſtical Courts have no power but what muſt be given them by the Statute Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>And therefore to come nearer to the matter, I ſhall ſet down what Laws have been ſince made in their favour, and what againſt them. Which is thus:</p>
            <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth being a Proteſtant, and having a wiſe and honeſt Council about him, foreſeeing the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit did accrue to the Crown and whole Nation by thoſe good Laws made in his Fathers time, made a Law that takes away all ſcruple and doubt whatſoever about the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Courts, and gives them not ſo much as power to hold any Courts in their own name, nor to uſe their own Seal, although they were ſuffered to act by, from, and under the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51917:8"/>King, according to the Laws made by his Father. And it appears by the Statute, Entituled, <hi>viz.</hi> An Act for the Election of Biſhops.</p>
            <p>Which Act, for the better information I have inſerted at large, hoping thoſe worthy Spiritual men will vouchſafe the reading it. Which is as follows:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foraſmuch as the Elections of Arch-Biſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> by the Deans and Chapters within the Kings Majeſties Realms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>at this preſent time, be as well to the long delay, as to the great coſts and charges of ſuch perſons, as the Kings Majeſty gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth any Arch-Biſhoprick or Biſhoprick unto: And whereas the ſaid Elections be in very déed no Elections, but only by a Writ of</hi> Conge d'Eſlire, <hi>have colours, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows or pretences of Elections, ſerving nevertheleſs to no purpoſe, and ſéeming alſo derogatory and prejudicial to the Prerogative Royal, to whom only appertaineth the Collation and gift of all Arch-Biſhopricks, and Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricks, and Suffragan Biſhops within his Highneſs ſaid Realms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, Wales, <hi>and other his Dominions and Marches: For a due reformation hereof, Be it therefore enacted by the Kings Highneſs, with the aſſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by Authority of the ſame, That from henceforth no ſuch</hi> Conge d'Eſlire <hi>be granted, nor Election of any Arch-Biſhop or Biſhop by the Dean and Chapter made: But that the King may by his Letters Patents at all times when any Arch-Biſhoprick or Biſhoprick is void, confer the ſame to any perſon to whom the King ſhall think méet: The which Collations ſo by the Kings Letters Patents made, and delivered to the perſon whom the King ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſame Arch-Biſhoprick or Biſhoprick, or to his ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Proctor or Attorney, ſhall ſtand to all intents, conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and purpoſes, to as much and the ſame effect, as though</hi> Conge d'Eſlire <hi>had béen given, the Election duly made, and the ſame confirmed. And thereupon the ſaid perſon to whom the ſaid Arch-Biſhoprick, Biſhoprick, or Suffraganſhip is ſo conferred, collated or given, may be conſecrated, and ſue his Livery or</hi> Ouſter le Main, <hi>and do other things as well as if the ſaid Ceremonies and Elections had béen done and made.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51917:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided always, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that every ſuch perſon, to whom any collation and gift of any Arch-Biſhoprick or Suffraganſhip ſhall be given or collated by the King, his Heirs or Sure eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, ſhall pay, do and yield to all and every perſon all ſuch fées, intereſts, and duties, as of old time hath béen accuſtomed to be done, any thing in this Act or in any other to the contrary hereof in any wiſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And whereas the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops, and other Spiritual perſons in this Realm, do uſe to make and ſend out their ſummons, citations and other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, in their own names, and in ſuch form and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as was uſed in the time of the uſurped power of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>contrary to the form and order of the ſummons and proceſs of the Common Law uſed in this Realm</hi> (<hi>ſéeing that all Authority of Iuriſdiction, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, is derived and deducted from the Kings Majeſty as ſupreme head of theſe Churches, and Realms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and ſo juſtly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Clergy of the ſaid Realms, that all Courts Eccleſiaſtical within the ſaid two Realms</hi>) <hi>be kept by no other power or authority, either foreign or within the Realm, but by the authority of his moſt excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. Be it therefore further enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that all ſummons and citations, or other Proceſs Eccleſiaſtical, in all ſuits and cauſes of Inſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt party and party, and all cauſes of Correction, and all cauſes of Baſtardy or Bigamy, or enquiry</hi> de jure patronatus, <hi>Probates of Teſtaments, and Commiſſions of Adminiſtrations of perſons deceaſed, and all Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittances of, and upon account made by the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Adminiſtrators, or Collectors of goods of any dead perſon, be from the firſt day of</hi> July <hi>next following, made in the name, and with the ſtyle of the Ring, as it is in Writs Original or Iudicial at the Common Law: And that the Teſt thereof he in the name of the Arch-Biſhop or Biſhop, or other, having Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, who hath the Commiſſion and grant of the Authority Eccleſiaſtical immediately from the Kings Highneſs, and that his Commiſſary, Official or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, exerciſing Iuriſdiction under him, ſhall put his name in the Citation or Proceſs after the Teſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51917:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Further be it enacted by the Authority afore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, That all manner of perſon or perſons, who have the exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction ſhall have from the firſt day of</hi> July <hi>before expreſſed in their Seals of Office, the Kings Highneſs Arms decently ſet, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Arms for the knowledge of the Dioceſs, and ſhall uſe no other Seal of Iurisdiction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> where his Majeſties Arms be ingraven, upon pain that if any perſon ſhall uſe Eccleſiaſtical Iurisdiction</hi> (<hi>after the day before expreſſed</hi>) <hi>in this Realm of</hi> England, Wales, <hi>or other his Dominions or Territories, and not ſend or make out the Ciration of Proceſs in the Kings name, or uſe any Seal of Iurisdiction other thau before limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that every ſuch Offender ſhall incur, and run in the Kings Majeſties diſpleaſure and indignation, and ſuffer Impriſonment at his Highneſs will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided that no more, nor other Fées be taken or paid for the Seal and Writing of any Citations or other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs than was heretofore accuſtomed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided alſo, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That the Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>for the time being, ſhall uſe his own Seal and in his own name, in all Faculties and Diſpenſations according to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of an Act thereof made: And that the ſaid Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Biſhops ſhall make, admit, order, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their Chancellours, Officials, Commiſſaries, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates, Proctors, and other their Officers, Miniſters and Subſtitutes, and Commiſſions of Suffragan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, in their own names, under their own Seals, in ſuch manner and form as they have heretofore uſed: And ſhall certifie to the Court of Tenths their Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitates under their own names and Seals, as heretofore they have uſed, and according to the Statute in that caſe made and provided: And likewiſe ſhall make collations, preſentations, gifts, inſtitutions, and inductions of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, Letters of Order, or Diſmiſſories, under their own Names and Seals, as they have heretofore accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed; any thing in this Act contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51917:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided always, and be it Enactes by the Authority aforeſaid, that all Proceſs hereafter to be made or awarded by any Eccleſiaſtical perſon or perſons, for the Tryal of any Plea or Pleas, or matter depending, or that horeaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall depend in any of the Kings Courts of Records at the Common Law, and limited by the Laws and Cuſtoms of this Realm, to the Spiritual Courts to try the ſame, that the Certificate of the ſame, alter the Tryal thereof, ſhall de made in the Kings name for the time being, and with the ſtyle of the ſanle King, and under the Seal of the Biſhop, graved with the Kings Arms, with the name of the Biſhop or Spiritual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, being to the Teſt of the ſame Proceſs and Certificate, and to every of them.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>This being then the Law that not only the power of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Courts, and all manner of Juriſdiction muſt be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from and under the King, but alſo if they hold any, it muſt be in the Kings name with his Arms in their Seals, and all Proceſs muſt have the Kings Title and not their own, otherwiſe than to the Teſt of the Proceſs as in judicial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in other Courts.</p>
            <p>If this be ſo, as there is no man dare own the contrary, then what colour have the Biſhops in their Spiritual Courts at this day to hold them in their own names, and to ſend out Proceſs under their own Seals as if they were all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramount the King, and even as big as the Pope himſelf? for ſo runs their Proceſs, <hi>viz.</hi> I cite you to appear before me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at ſuch a place. Now I would feign know what this [I] is, whether it be I Pope, or I Jeſuite, or I Turk, that dare be thus bold with the Law and their Soveraign, not only in eclipſing his Prerogative, but indeed fetting themſelves above him and the Law too: ſurely ſhould but a Fanatick dare to do but one half ſo much, it would be both hell and damnation, if not the Fanatick Plot, ſo much talked of by theſe great Loyaliſts.</p>
            <p>But I muſt now come to ſhew you what they pretend againſt this Law, for had they no excuſe at all they would not be legitimate.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51917:10"/>
            <p>Their pretence therefore is this, that Queen <hi>Marr</hi> when ſhe came to the Crown repealed all Laws that diminiſhed the authority of the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> among which, they ſay, this Act was one, but how this will help them, the Reader may judge, if it were ſo, which cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>For thus it is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> &amp; <hi>2</hi> P. &amp; M. Cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> in the firſt and ſecond of <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> an Act was made, <hi>viz.</hi> An Act repealing all Articles and Proviſions made againſt the See Apoſtolick of <hi>Rome</hi> ſince the <hi>20th</hi> of K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. and for eſtabliſhing all Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical poſſeſſions and hereditaments conveyed to the Laity.</p>
            <p>In this Statute there are diverſe Acts repealed by name, but this Act of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. is not named, but is ſuppoſed to be implyed, becauſe that was againſt the Juriſdiction of <hi>Rome,</hi> but if that be a good repeal without naming, the Statute it ought to be well conſidered;</p>
            <p>However if it were ſo, that will ſtand them in but ſmall ſtead, for in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s reign all this whole Statute of Repeal is repealed; then if ſo, thoſe Acts are in force again. And ſo this excuſe for holding Courts in their own names, and by the Authority of their Canons cannot help them, but leaves them in the ſame condition as in <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Eighth and <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's time, in which they had no power at all.</p>
            <p>This plainly appears by the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. which reſtores to the Crown the Ancient Juriſdiction, and aboliſhes all foreign power in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, and repeals the Statute of Repeal made in the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi> Which is as follows:</p>
            <p>An Act to reſtore to the Crown the ancient Juriſdiction over the Eſtate Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Eliz. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and aboliſhing all foreign power repugnant to the ſame. Which begins thus:</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51917:10"/>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Moſt humbly beſeech your moſt Excellent Majeſty your faithful and Obedient Subjects, The Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this your preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled: That where in the time of the reign of your moſt dear Father of Worthy Memory, King</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 8th. <hi>divers good Laws and Statutes were made and Eſtabliſhed, as well for the utter extinguiſhment and puting away of all uſurped and Foreign powers and Authorities out of this your Realm, and other your Highneſs Dominions and Countries, as alſo for the reſtoring and uniting to the Imperial Crown of this Realm, the Ancient Iuriſdictions, Authorities, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorities, and Preheminencies to the ſame of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing and appertaining, by reaſon whereof, we your moſt humble and obedient Subjects, from the five and twentieth year of the reign of your ſaid dear Father, were continually kept in good order, and were diſburdened of diverſe great and intollerable charges and exactions before that time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully taken, and exacted by ſuch Forreign power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as before that was uſurped, until ſuch time as all the ſaid good Laws and Statutes by one Act of Parliament made in the firſt and ſecond years of the Reigns of the late King</hi> Philip, <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary <hi>your Highneſs Siſter intituted an Act repealing all Statutes, Articles and proviſions made againſt the See Apoſtolick of</hi> Rome; <hi>ſince the twentieth year of King</hi> Henry <hi>the eight, and alſo for the Eſtabliſhment of all Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical poſſeſſions and Hereditaments conveyed to the Laity, were all clearly repealed and made void, as by the ſame Act of Repeal more at large doth and may appear; By reaſon of which Act of Repeal, your ſaid humble Subjects were eftſoons brought under an uſurped Forreign power and Authority, and yet do remain in that bondage, to the intollerable charges of your loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, if ſome redreſs (by Authority of this your high Court of Parliament, with the aſſent of your Highneſs) be not had and provided.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>May it therefore pleaſe your Highneſs, for the repreſſing of the ſaid uſurped Forreign power, and the reſtoring of the Rites, Iuriſdictions and Preheminencies appertaining to the Imperial Crown of this your Realm, that it may be Enacted by Authority of this preſent Parliament. That the ſaid Act made in the firſt and ſecond years of the Reign of the ſaid late King</hi> Philip <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>and all and every branches, Clauſes and Articles therein contained (other then ſuch branches, Clauſes and Sentences, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall be excepted) may from the laſt day of this Seſſion of Parliament, by Authority of this preſent Parliament, be repealed, and ſhall from thenceforth be utterly void and of none effect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>16</label> 
                  <hi>And to the intent that all Vſurped and Forreign power and Authority Spiritual and Temporal, may for ever be clearly exting uiſhed, and never be uſed or obeyed within this Realm,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51917:11"/>or any other your Majeſties Dominions or Countries, May it pleaſe your Highneſs that it may be further enacted by the Authority aforeſaid. That no Forreign Prince, Perſon, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, State or Potentate, Spiritual or Temporal, ſhall at any time after the laſt day of this Seſſion of Parliament, uſe, entry or exerciſe any manner of power, Iuriſdiction, Superiority, Authority, Preheminence, or Priviledge Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or Eccleſiaſtical, within this Realm, or within any other your Majeſties Dominions or Countries that now be, or hereafter ſhall be, but from thence forth the ſame ſhall be clearly aboliſhed out of this Realm, and all other your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Dominions for ever; any Statute, Ordinance, Cuſtom, Conſtitutions, or any other matter or cauſe whatſoever to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>17</label> 
                  <hi>And that alſo it may pleaſe your Highneſs that it may be eſtabliſhed and enacted by the Authority aforeſaid that ſuch Iuriſdictions, Priviledges, Superiorities and Preheminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical as by any Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical power or Authority hath heretofore been or may fawfully be exerciſed or uſed for the Viſitation of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical State and Perſons, and for Reformation, order and correction of the ſame and of all manner of Errors, Herefies, Shiſmes, Abuſes, Offences, Contempts, and Enormities, ſhall for ever, by Authority of this preſent Parliament be united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Now by theſe Branches of this Statute it is moſt clear that all manner of Juriſdiction in Cauſes Spiritual and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical is more abſolutely inveſted in the Crown then ever before, ſo that if that of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, yet here it is paſt all doubt that Act is now by this more inforced then ever: And that it may appear more plain, that no Court Spiritual was to Act any more but by Authority from the Queen in the next Section of this Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Power was given to the Queen in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words to grant Commiſſions (to hold Courts) under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> or elſe by this Statute none could be held at all neither in their own name, nor in the name of the Queen, which branch of the ſaid Statute runs thus.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>18</label> 
                  <hi>And that your Highneſs your Heirs and Succeſſors, Kings or Queens of this Realm, ſhall have full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by vertue of this Act, by letters patents under the great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>to aſſign, name and authorize, when and as often as your Highneſs, your Heirs or Succeſſors ſhall think meet and Convenient, and for ſuch and ſo long time as ſhall pleaſe your Highneſs, your Heirs or Succeſſors
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51917:11"/>ſuch perſon or perſons being natural born Subjects to your Highneſs your Heirs and Succeſſors, as your Majeſty your Heirs or Succeſſors ſhall think meet to exerciſe, uſe, occupy and execute under your Highneſs your Heirs and Succeſſors, all member of Iuriſdictions, Priviledges, and Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nences in any wiſe touching or concerning any Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction within theſe your Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>or any other your Highneſs Dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ions and Countries, and to vis;it, reform, redreſs, order, correct, and amend all ſuch errors, heriſies, ſchiſms, abirſes, offences, contempts, and enormities whatſoever which by any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical power Authority or Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction can or may lawfully be reformed, ordered, redreſſed, corrected, reſtrained, or amended to the pleaſure of Almighty God, the increaſe of vertue, and the conſervation of the peace and unity of this Realm. And that ſuch perſon or perſons ſo to be named, aſſigned, authoriſed and appointed by your Highneſs, your Heirs or Succeſſors, after the ſaid Letters Patents to him or them made and delivered, as is aforeſaid, ſhall have full power and authority by vertue of this Act and of the ſaid Letters Patents under your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, your Heirs and Succeſſors, to exerciſe, uſe and execute all the premiſes; according to the Tenor and effect of the ſaid Letters Patents; any matter or cauſe to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Here it is moſt evident that the Queen had the only ſole power to nominate, and appoint by her Commiſſion under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> both lay-men as well as Biſhops to exerciſe Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction when and as often as ſhe pleaſed, and it is moſt evident it was not to be done at all without ſuch Commiſſions.</p>
            <p>But beſides this Law it was the practice both in the times of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James;</hi> That all the Biſhops, and the Spiritual Courts whatſoever were held by ſuch Commiſſions and to ſatisfie the Reader I have here inſerted a Copy of one of them taken out of the Rolls, <hi>Verbatim,</hi> viz.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter_of_appointments">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by the Grace of God,<note place="margin">Rot. <hi>9.</hi> Pars. <hi>10.</hi> Eliz.</note> 
                        <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <salute>To the Reverend Father in God <hi>Mathew Parker</hi> nominated Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and <hi>Edmond Grindale</hi> nominated Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> And to our right Truſty and well beloved Councellor <hi>Francis Knowls</hi> our Vice-chamberlain, and <hi>Ambroſe Cave</hi> Knight. And to our Truſty and well beloved <hi>Anthony Cooke</hi> and <hi>Thomas Smiths</hi> Knights, <hi>William Bill</hi> our Almoner, <hi>Walter Haddome</hi> and <hi>Thomas Sackford</hi> Maſters of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, <hi>Rowland Hill</hi> and <hi>William Cheſter</hi> Knights, <hi>Randoll
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51917:12"/>Cholmely</hi> and <hi>John Southcote</hi> Serjeants at the Law, <hi>William May</hi> Docter of Law, <hi>Francis Cave, Richard Goodrick</hi> and <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> Eſquires, <hi>Robert Weſton</hi> and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Hunck</hi> Doctors of Law, <hi>Greeting.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Where as our Parliament holden at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Five and Twentieth Day of <hi>Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and there continued and kept until the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Day of <hi>May</hi> then next following; Amongſt other things, there was Two Acts and Statutes made and Eſtabliſhed; the one Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>An Act for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of the Common-Prayer and Service in the Church, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments:</hi> And the other Intituled, <hi>An Act, Reſtoring to the Crown the Antient Juriſdiction of the State-Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual, and Aboliſhing all Forraign Power repugnant to the ſame.</hi> As by the ſame ſeveral Acts more at large doth appear: And whereas divers Seditious and Slanderous Perſons do not ceaſe dayly to invent and ſet forth falſe Rumours, Tales, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Slanders, not only againſt us and the ſaid good Laws and Statutes, but alſo have ſet forth divers Seditious Books within this our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> meaning thereby to move and procure Strife, Diviſion, Diſſention amongſt our Loving and Obedient Subjects, much to the Diſquieting of us and our People. Wherefore we earneſtly minding to have the ſame Acts before mentioned, to be duely put in Execution; and ſuch Perſons as ſhall hereafter Offend in any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Tenor and Effect of the ſaid ſeveral Statutes to be accordingly puniſhed; and haveing Eſpecial Truſt and Confidence in your Wiſdoms and Diſcretion, have Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, Aſſigned and Appointed you to be our Commiſſioners. And by theſe Preſents, do give our full Power and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to you, or Six of you; whereof you the ſaid <hi>Matthew Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Edmond Grendale, Thomas Smith, Walter Haddon, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> and <hi>Gilbert Gerrard,</hi> to be one from time to time hereafter, dureing our pleaſure, to Inquire as well by the Oaths of Twelve Good and Lawful Men; as alſo by Witneſſes, and all other Lawful ways and means you can deviſe, for all Offences, Miſdoers and Miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors done and committed of them, and hereafter to be committed or done contrary to the Tenor and Effect of the ſaid ſeveral Acts and Statutes, and either of them; and alſo of all and ſingular Heretical Opinions, Seditious Books, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, Conſpiracies, falſe Rumours, Tales, Seditious-Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behaviours, Slanderous Words, or Shewings, publiſhed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, or ſet forth; or hereafter to be publiſhed, invented, or ſet forth by any Perſon or Perſons, againſt us, or contrary,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51917:12"/>or againſt any of the Laws or Statutes of this our Realm, or againſt the quiet Governance and rule of our People and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, in any County, City, Burrough, or other place or places within this our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and of all and every the Coad jutors, Councellors, Comforters, Procurers and Abbet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of any ſuch Offender: And further, We do give Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority to you or ſix of you, Whereof the ſaid <hi>Mathow Parker, Edmond Grindale, Thomas Smith, Walter Haddon, Thomas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> or <hi>Gilbert Gerrard,</hi> to be one from time to time hereafter during our pleaſure, as well to hear and determine all the premiſes, as alſo to inquire, hear, and determine all and ſingular enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, diſturbance, and misbehaviors done and committed or hereafter to be done and committed in any Church or Chappel or againſt any Divine ſervice, or the Miniſter or Miniſters of the ſame, contrary to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, and alſo to enquire oft ſearch out and to order correct and reform all ſuch perſons as hereafter ſhall or will obſtinately abſent themſelves from Church, and ſuch Divine Service as by the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, is appointed to be had and uſed. And alſo we do give and grant full power, and Authority to you or ſix of you whereof you the ſaid <hi>Mathew Parker, Edmond Grindale, Thomas Smith, Walter Haddon, Thomas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> or <hi>Gilbert Gerrard,</hi> to be one from time to time and at all times during our pleaſure, to viſit, reform, redreſs, order, correct, and amend in all places within this our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> all ſuch Errors, Hereſies, Schiſms, Abuſes, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, Contempts, and Enormities Spiritual and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical whereſoever, which by any Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Power, Authority, or Juriſdiction can or may be lawfully reformed, ordered, redreſſed, corrected, reſtrained or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the pleaſure of Almighty God, the encreaſe of Vertue, and the Conſervation of the Peace and Unity of this our Realm; and according to the Authority and power limitted, given and Appointed by any Laws or Statutes of this Realm. And alſo that you and ſix of you whereof the ſaid <hi>Mathew Parker, Edmond Grindale, Thomas Smith, Walter Haddon, Thomas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> or <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> to be one, ſhall likewiſe have full power and Authority from time to time to enquire oft and ſearch out all Mercileſimen quarrels, Vagarant, and ſuſpected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons within our City of <hi>London,</hi> and ten Miles Compaſs about the ſame City, and of all aſſaults, and affrays done
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51917:13"/>and committed within the ſame City, and the compaſs aforeſaid. And alſo we give full power and Authority unto you and ſix of you as before ſumerly to hear, and finally determine according to your diſcretions and by the Laws of this Realm all Cauſes and Complaints of all them which in reſpect of Religion or for lawfully Matrimony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and allowed by the ſame where injuriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived defrauded or ſpoiled of their Lands, Goods, Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, Rights, Dignities, Livings, Offices Spiritual or Temporal; and them ſo deprived as before, to reſtore unto their ſaid livings, and to put them into poſſeſſion amoveing the Uſurpers in convenient ſpeed, as it ſhall ſeem to your diſcretions good by your Letters, Meſſage, or otherwiſe all fruſtratory appellations clearly rejected. And further we do give Power and Authority unto you, and ſix of you whereof you the ſaid <hi>Mathew Parker, Edmond Grindale, Thomas Smith, Walter Hadden, Thomas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> or <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> to be one by vertue hereof full Power and Authority, not only to hear and determine the ſame and all other Offences and matters before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and rehearſed, but alſo all other Notorious and manifeſt advoutry and Fornications, and Eccleſiaſtical crimes and offences within this our Realm according to your Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Conſciences and Diſcretions willing and commanding you or ſix of you, whereof you the ſaid <hi>Mathew Parker, Edmond Grindale, Thomas Smith, Walter Haddon, Thomas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> or <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> to be one from time to time hereafter to uſe and deviſe all ſuch pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick ways, and means for the Tryal and Searching out of all the premiſes as by you or ſix of you as aforeſaid ſhall be thought moſt expedient neceſſary, and upon due proof had, and the Offence or Offences before ſpecified or any of them ſufficiently proved againſt any perſon or perſons, as by you or ſix of you, by confeſſion of the party or by lawful Witneſſes or by any other due means before you or ſix of you whereof the ſaid <hi>Mathew Parker, Edmond Grindale, Thomas Smith, Walter Haddon, Thomas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> or <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> to be one, that then you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, ſhall have full power and Authority to award ſuch Puniſhment to every Offender by fine Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment or otherwiſe by all or any of the ways afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and to take ſuch order for the redreſs of the ſame as to your Wiſdoms and Diſcretions or ſix of you, whereof the ſaid <hi>Mathew Parker, Edmond Grindale, Thomas Smith,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51917:13"/>Walter Haddon, Thomas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> or <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> to be one to call before you or ſix of you, as aforeſaid from time to time, all and every Offender or Offenders, and ſuch as by you and ſix of you as aforeſaid ſhall ſeem to be ſuſpected perſons in any of the premiſes, and alſo, All ſuch Witneſſes as you or ſix of you, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſhall think fit to be called before you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, and them and every of them to examine upon their Corporal Oaths, for the better Tryal and opening of the premiſſes or any part thereof. And if you or ſix of you as aforeſaid ſhall find any perſon or perſons obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate or diſobedient, either in their apparrel before you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, at your calling and Commandment or elſe not accompliſhing or not obeying your Orders, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and Commandments, in any thing touching the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes or any part thereof, that then you or ſix of you as aforeſaid ſhall have full Power and Authority to commit the ſame perſon or perſons ſo offending, toward there to remain until he or they ſhall be by you or ſix of you as aforeſaid enlarged and delivered. And further we do give you and ſix of you whereof the ſaid <hi>Mathew Parker, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Grindale, Thomas Smith, Walter Haddon, Thomas Sack-ford, Richard Godrick,</hi> or <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> to be one full Power and Authority, by theſe preſents to take and receive by your Diſcretions of every Offender, or ſuſpected perſon to be convented and brought before you a Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance or Recognizances Obligation or Obligations to our uſe in ſuch ſum or ſums of Mony as to you or ſix of you as aforeſaid ſhall ſeem Convenient, as well for their perſonal appearance, before you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, as alſo for the performance and accompliſhment of your Orders and Decrees, in caſe you or ſix of you as aforeſaid ſhall ſee it ſo convenient. And further our will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, that you ſhall appoint Our Truſty and well beloved <hi>John Skinner</hi> to be your Regiſter of all your Acts, Decrees, and Preceedings by vertue of this Commiſſion, and in his default one other ſufficient perſon, and that you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, ſhall give ſuch Allowance to the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter for his pains, and his Clerks to be levied of the fines, and other profits that ſhall ariſe by force of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; and your devices in the premiſſes as to your Diſcretions ſhall be thought meet. And further our will and pleaſure is, that you or ſix of you as aforeſaid ſhall name and appoint one other ſufficient perſon to gather up,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51917:14"/>and receive all ſuch ſums of Mony as ſhall be aſſeſſed, and Taxed by you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, for any fine or fines upon any perſon or perſons for their Offenees. And that you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, by Bill or Bills ſigned with your hands, ſhall and may aſſign and appoint as well as to the ſaid perſon for his pains in receiving the ſaid ſums. As alſo to your Meſſengers and Attendants upon you for their trouble pains and charges to be ſuſtained for us about the premiſes or any part thereof ſuch ſums of Mony for their rewards as by you or ſix of you as aforeſaid ſhall be thought expedient, willing and commanding you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, after the time of this our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion expired to certifie unto our Courts of Exchequer, as well the name of the ſaid Receiver as alſo a Note of ſuch fines as ſhall be ſet or taxed before you, to the intent that upon the determination of Account of the ſaid Receiver we ſhall be anſwered of that to us ſhall juſtly appertain, Willing and Commanding alſo our Auditors, and other Officers upon the ſight of the ſaid Bills, ſigned with the hands of you or ſix of you as aforeſaid, to make unto the ſaid Receiver due allowances according to the ſaid Bills upon his account. Wherefore we will and Command you our Commiſſioners with Dilligence to Execute the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes with effect any of our Laws, Statutes, Proclamations or other grants priviledges or Ordinances, which be or may ſeem to be contrary to the premiſes notwithſtanding. And more, we will and command all and ſingular Juſtices of peace, Majors, Sheriffs, Bayliffs, Conſtables, and other our Officers, Miniſters, and faithful Subjects to be ayding help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and aſſiſting you, and at Commandment in the Due Execution hereof as they tender our pleaſure, and will Anſwer the contrary at their utmoſt perills. And we will and grant theſe our Letters, Patents, ſhall be a ſufficient Warrant and diſcharge for you, and every of you againſt us our Heirs and Succeſſors, and all and every other perſon or perſons whatſover they be of and for or concerning the premiſes, or any parcel thereof, of or for the Execution of this our Commiſſion or any part thereof Witneſs the Queen at </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 
                        <date>the Nineteenth day of <hi>July,</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Anno Regni Regine Elizabethe Primo.Per ipſam Reginam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51917:14"/>
            <p>Thus by what hath been ſaid, you ſee both by Statute, Law and Preſident, of the very Commiſſion themſelves which the Biſhops Acted by, it is clear they ought not to Act or Hold any Courts whatſoever in their own Names, nor in the Kings, without his Special Commiſſion under the great Seal of <hi>England.</hi> And altho' there was a Statute made in the Firſt of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Intituled, <hi>An Act for Repeal of certain Statutes made in the time of King</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>vid.</hi> 1 Jac. <hi>Cap.</hi> 25.</note> yet by the Firſt of King <hi>James,</hi> Cap. 25. that Statute of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal is Repealed, ſo that cannot ſtand our Spiritual Perſons in no ſtead at all, tho' my Lord <hi>Cook</hi> did inſiſt upon it in his <hi>2d.</hi> Inſtitutions.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, In the <hi>8th</hi> Year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> you will find the very ſame thing aſſerted by the Act made,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>8</hi> Eliz. Cap. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 8 <hi>Eliz.</hi> Cap. 1. Intituled, <hi>An Act declaring the making and Conſecrating of the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of this Realm, to be good, Lawful and Perfect.</hi> In which Act, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. it is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared thus, <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Firſt, It is very well known to all degrees of this Realm, that the late King of moſt famous Memory, King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, as well by all the Clergy then of this Realm in their ſeveral Convocations; as alſo by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons aſſembled in divers of his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, was juſtly and rightly recognized and knowledged to have the ſupream Power, Iurisdiction, Order, Rule and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over all the Eſtate Eccleſiaſtical of the ſame, and the ſame Power, Iurisdiction and Authority did uſe accordingly: And that alſo the ſaid late King in the</hi> 25th <hi>Year of his Reign, did by Authority of Parliament amongſt other things, ſet forth a certain Order of the manner and form how Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Biſhops within this Realm, and other his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſhould be Elected and made, as by the ſame more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth: And that alſo the late King of worthy Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, King</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth, did Lawfully ſucceed the ſaid late King</hi> Henry <hi>his Father in the Imperial Crown of this Realm, and did juſtly poſſeſs and enjoy all the ſame Power, Iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Authority before mentioned, as a thing to him deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the ſame Imperial Crown, and ſo uſed the ſame du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Life. And alſo that the ſaid late King</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth in his time, by Authority of Parliament, cauſed a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Vertuous Book, Intituled,</hi> The Book of Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Adminiſtration of Sacraments, and other Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in the Church of <hi>England; <hi>to be made and ſet forth, not only for one Vniform Order of Service, Common-Prayer, and the Adminiſtration of Sacraments, to be uſed within this Realm, and other his Dominions; but alſo did add and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51917:15"/>put to the ſame Book a very good and Godly Order of the manner and form how Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Prieſts, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons and Miniſters, ſhauld from time to time be Conſecrated, made and ordered within this Realm and other his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as by the ſame more plainly will and may appear. And although in the time of the late Queen</hi>
               </hi> Mary, <hi>as well the ſaid Act and Statute made in the</hi> 25th <hi>Year of the Reign of the ſaid late King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, as alſo the ſeveral Acts and Statutes made in the Second, Third, Fourth, Fifth, and Sixth Years of the Reign of the ſaid late King</hi> Edward, <hi>for the Authorizing and Allowing of the ſaid Book of Common-Prayer, and other the premiſes, amongſt divers other Acts and Statutes touching the ſaid Supream Authority, were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed: yet nevertheleſs, at the Parliament holden at</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, <hi>in the firſt Year of the Reign of our Soveraign Lady the Queens Majeſty that now is by one other Act and Statute there made, all ſuch Iurisdictions, Priviledges, Superiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Preheminences Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical, as by any Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Power and Authority hath heretofore been, or may Lawfully be uſed over the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal State of this Realm, and the Order, Reformation, and Correction of the ſame, is fully and abſolutely by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſame Parliament, united and annexed to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown of this Realm: And by the ſame Act and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, there is alſo given to the Queens Highneſs, her Heirs and Succeſſors, Kings and Queens of this Realm, full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority by Letters Patents under the great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>from time to time to asſign, name and authorize ſuch Perſon or Perſons as ſhe or they ſhall think meet and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to exerciſe, uſe, occupy and execute under her Highneſs all manner of Iurisdictions, Priviledges, Preheminencies and Authorities in any wiſe touching or concerning any Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or Eccleſiaſtical Power or Iurisdiction within this Realm, or any other Her Highneſs Dominions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Here again you ſee that the very Commiſſions are again Confirmed, and all Eccleſiaſtical Power abſolutely in the Queen to make and Appoint by her Commiſſion whom She pleaſe to exerciſe Spiritual Juriſdiction, and no Man ever pretended this Statute to be touched.</p>
            <p>This being the Caſe to the end of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, we muſt ſee what was done in King <hi>James</hi> time, and ſo to this Day.</p>
            <p>In King <hi>James</hi> time the Biſhops and Eccleſiaſtical Courts were holden as in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> time, as is moſt apparent; for meeting with an Objection, that the Biſhops held Courts in their own names time out of mind, notwithſtanding the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51917:15"/>and that the long cuſtome would excuſe them therein, eſpecially when the King did permit it. I took an occaſion to inform my ſelf from the Journals and Records, and do find that the Eccleſiaſtical Power was held and uſed in the time of King <hi>James,</hi> under him by Vertue of Commiſſion, as before, and to put it out of all doubt, I ſhall demonſtrate it thus:<note place="margin">Vide Journ. ho. Lords. <hi>7</hi> Jac. &amp; <hi>10. 1610.</hi>
               </note> 7 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> A Diſpute aroſe about the Spiritual Courts of their Extortion and going beyond their Commiſſions; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament complained to the King againſt the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Courts, and pray that no more ſuch power may be given them by Commiſſions, And a Queſtion aroſe in the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>Jacobi,</hi> whether they had any power at all; in full Parliament it was Reſolved, and the King gave his Anſwer, and the Judgement of the Houſe of Peers, <hi>That they had no Power but by the Kings Commiſſion, which he would take care for the time to come that it ſhould not be any Burthen to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Which Anſwer and Judgement in Parliament you have here <hi>in hec Verba</hi> ſet down, <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Parliamentary_statement">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Die Lunae, Viz. 23 die <hi>July,</hi> 1610. Poſt Meridiem.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His Majeſties Anſwer delivered to the whole Aſſembly of both Houſes, the</hi> 23d <hi>of</hi> July, 1610. <hi>unto certain Grievances former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered to His Majeſty by the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Commons Houſe of Parliament, touching the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and dangerous extent of the Statute of</hi> 1 Eliz. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. Our Approved care for the well Ordering of Eccleſiaſtical-Courts and Cauſes, ought to baniſh from the conceits of our loving Subjects all needleſs and imaginary fears: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we are pleaſed to aſſure them by Our Royal Promiſe, That our Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſions ſhall not be Directed to ſingular Perſons, but to ſuch a number of Commiſſioners, and them ſo elected as the weight of ſuch Cauſes doth require: And that no Definitive Sentence be given or pronounced by ſuch our Commiſſioners, under the number of Seven of them, ſitting in Court, or Five at the leaſt, and that in only caſe of Neceſſity. And further, That we ſhall not take Advantage by any power given us by that Statute, to grant forth any forms of Commiſſion exceeding further then to Impriſonment and Reaſonable Fine. And likewiſe, That We ſhall reſtrain ſuch our General Commiſſions to the number of Two, the one for this Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the other for that of <hi>York;</hi> Beſides we are Reſolved to Eſtabliſh ſuch an Order touching the uſe and practice of Our ſaid Commiſſion, as that none of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51917:16"/>our Loving Subjects ſhall be drawn from remote places, either to <hi>London</hi> or <hi>York,</hi> except it ſhall be for ſuch exorbitant of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences as are fit to be made exemplary; And for the enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes in particular, as it is a matter full of Difficulty, ſo it is needful (as we ſuppoſe,) conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they are already limited and confined as no Antient Canon or Spiritual Laws are in force, that are either contrary to the Laws, Statutes, or Cuſtomes of this Realm, or tend to the Dammage or Hurt of our Prerogative Royal.</p>
                  <p>For the Grievances apprehended in the Commiſſion, Firſt a Soveraign King being <hi>Mixta Perſona,</hi> and having Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as well in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical as Temporal, it was with great Wiſdom ordained (Matters of the Church being many ways impugned, and the Cenſures of it grown into contempt) That there ſhould be a Commiſſion conſiſting as well of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral as Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, who might have power for one Offence at one time and by one ſentence to inflict as there ſhould be cauſe, both Spiritual and Temporal puniſhment, but as to the Inquiry by Juries, it hath not for many Years been practiſed. And we are content, that hereafter it be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in our Commiſſion; And concerning Appeals, the uſe hath always been to exclude them in Commiſſions of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; And yet if any of our Subjects ſhall be juſtly grieved with any Sentence given by our Commiſſioners, we ſhall be content, as we find juſt cauſe, to grant unto them a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Review: Alſo for the Execution of divers Statutes, aimed at in your Grievances, although it hath been from time to time committed in ſome ſort unto our Commiſſioners. And that every ſuch Commiſſion hath been ſtill penned by the Attorney-General, with the Advice of the chief Temporal Judges; yet we are well pleaſed, and will give command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accordingly, that our Temporal and Eccleſiaſtical Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, aſſiſted with our Learned Council, ſhall confer together concerning the Exceptions by you taken, to the end that hereafter our ſaid Commiſſioners may have no further pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to intermeddle with the Execution of any part of the ſaid Statutes, then it ſhall be found fit for our Service, neceſſary for the ſuppreſſing of Popery and Schiſm, and no ways repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Laws and Pollices of this our Realm: But for making any Innovations in the forms and proceedings here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore uſed by our ſaid Commiſſioners, we know no cauſe to depart therein from the Examples of our Progenitors, nor from that which the Laws of this our Kingdom hath Approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And touching Fees, ſince it is a Court by Statute erected
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51917:16"/>and no Fees in the Statute expreſſed, it was very fit, That the Commiſſioners ſhould have Authority to limit and Appoint to every Officer his Reaſonable Fees: And we will commend the further care thereof to ſome Principal perſon of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, to take a view of them, and as to reform what they find amiſs, ſo to Eſtabliſh ſuch as ſhall be Moderate and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, touching the Grievances found in the Execution of the Commisſion. We know that there is no Commisſion nor Court either of Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal Juriſdiction, but may be ſubject more or leſs to Abuſe in the execution of their Authority. Nevertheleſs, it is Our part to have our Ear open to receive Complaints of that kind eſpecially from our Parliament, when we ſhall find them to be juſt: And therefore our purpoſe is to ſee ſuch Reformation made of all Abuſes made in the execution of the ſaid Commisſion, as may beſt procure the eaſe of Our Subject, from charge of Vexation; And ſuch puniſhment to be inflicted upon any Purſivants or other inferior Miniſters which ſhall be Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as may repreſs ſuch Miſdemeanors in time to come.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Sure if this Record be conſidered, there is ground enough to juſtifie that the Spiritual Courts cannot be holden but by the Kings Commisſion; Therefore I need ſay no more, the Caſe being plain the Law was ſo to this Year of 1610. which I ſet down the rather becauſe a uſe will be made of it by and by.</p>
            <p>But in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's time, the Biſhops caſt about them how to get rid of theſe Shackles; And therefore in Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi>'s time, the point about Holding Courts in their own Names, without the Kings Commisſion, was by him ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and in the Star-Chamber where he ruled the Roſt got the Judges there, tho' it was but an extra Judicial Judgment to declare in their favour, which was eaſie enough to be done when both the Judges and His Grace were reſolved upon the point, for thoſe very Judges moſt of them were the ſame that gave their Judgment about the Shipp-Money; And we know what became of that Judgment and them: And for your Prelate he met with his due at <hi>Tower-Hill</hi> after, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Lordſhip had finiſhed his Miniſtry, ſo prevalent he was, that I am told he got a Proclamation to publiſh the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra judicial Opinion, which made a great noiſe in the World, for Noyſe and Decency was all along the Cheat that was put upon the People in thoſe Days by that Prelate and his Gang.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51917:17"/>
            <p>But I think no Man will ſay that that Extra Judicial Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is either equal with the Statute Law, or with the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Parliament, therefore I ſhall ſay no more, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>After that Extra Judical Opinion of the Judges, and by means of the long Intervals of Parliament, the Spiritual Courts as well as the Star-Chamber, were Lords Paramont, and ſo great, that they became a moſt Heavy Burden to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all ſorts; therefore before the Troubles began, the Parliament in 16 <hi>Car. primi,</hi> made an Act to take away the Power that was given by the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> for the Grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Commisſions at all; by which means they well knew that no Courts could be held at all; And therefore an Act paſſed to Repeal that Branch of the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> which was only one Clauſe about the granting Commisſions, as by the Act of <hi>Car. primi,</hi> appears, and all Spiritual Courts were utterly Aboliſhed by that Act, The Title of the Act runs thus, <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="act">
               <body>
                  <head>A Repeal of the Brauch of a Statute, <hi>primo Elizabethe,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Commiſſions for Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhereas in the Parliament holden in the firſt Year of the Reign of the late Queen</hi> Elizabeth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>16</hi> Car. c. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>late Queen of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>there was an Act made and Eſtabliſhed, Intituled,</hi> An Act Reſtoring to the Crown the Antient Juriſdiction over the State Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual, and Aboliſhing all Forreign Power Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the ſame. <hi>In which Act amongſt other things there is contained one Clauſe, Branch, Article or Sentence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it was Enacted to this effect, Namely, That the ſaid late Queens Highneſs, her Heirs and Succeſſors, Kings or Queens of this Realm, ſhould have full Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by vertue of that Act, by Letters Patents under the Great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>to Asſign, Name and Authorize, when and as often as her Highneſs, her Heirs or Succeſſours, ſhould think meet and Convenient: and for ſuch, and ſo long time as ſhould pleaſe her Highneſs, her Heirs or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, ſuch Perſon or Perſons being Natural Born Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to her Highneſs, her Heirs or Succeſſors, as her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, her Heirs or Succeſſors ſhould think meet to exerciſe, uſe, occupy and execute under her Highneſs, her Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, all manner of Iurisdictions, Priviledges, Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies, in any wiſe touching or concerning any Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Iurisdiction within theſe her Realms of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51917:17"/>
                     <hi>or</hi> Ireland, <hi>or any other her Highneſs Dominions and Countries, and to viſit, reform, redreſs, order, correct and amend all ſuch Errors, Hereſies, Schiſms, Abuſes, Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Contempts, and Enormities whatſoever, which by any manner Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Power, Authority or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction, can or may Lawfully be Reformed, Ordered, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed, Corrected, Reſtrained, or Amended to the Pleaſure of Almighty God, the increaſe of Vertue, and the Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Peace and Vnity of this Realm. And that ſuch Perſon or Perſons ſo to be Named, Asſigned, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized and appointed by her Highneſs, her Heirs or Succeſſors, after the ſaid Letters Patents to him or them made and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered as aforeſaid, ſhould have full Power and Authority by Vertue of that Act, and of the ſaid Letters Patents under her Highneſs, her Heirs or Succeſſors, to exerciſe, uſe and Execute all the Premiſes, accordidg to the Tenor and Effect of the ſaid Letters Patents, any matter or cauſe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And whereas by culler of ſome VVords in the aforeſaid Branch of the ſaid Act, whereby Commisſioners are Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to Execute their Commisſion, according to the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and effect of the Kings Letters Patents grounded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the ſaid Commisſioners have to the great and in-Sufferable VVrong and Oppresſion of the Kings Subjects uſed to Fine and Impriſon them, and to exerciſe other Authority not belonging to Eccleſiaſtical Iurisdiction reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by that Act, and divers other great Miſchiefs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies have alſo enſued to the Kings Subjects, by reaſon of the ſaid Branch and Commisſions iſſued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and the Executions thereof: Therefore for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presſing and Preventing of the aforeſaid Abuſes, Miſchiefs, and inconveniencies in time to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be it Enacted by the Kings Moſt Excellent Majeſty, and the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament Aſſembled, and by Authority of the ſame. That the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Branch, Clauſe, Article or Sentence contained in the ſaid Act, and every word, matter and thing Contained in that Branch, Clauſe, Article or Sentence, ſhall from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be Repealed, Annulled, Revoked, Annihilated and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly made void for Edect; any thing in the ſaid Act to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And be it alſo Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That no Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop or Vicar-General, nor any Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor Official, or Commiſſary of any Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, a Vicar General nor any Ordinary whatſoever, nor any
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51917:18"/>other Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Iudge, Officer, or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Iuſtice, nor any other Perſon or Perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, exerciſing Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Power, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or Iurisdiction, by any Grant, Licence, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misſion of the Kings Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or by any Power or Authority derived from the King, his Heirs or Succeſſors, or otherwiſe, ſhall from and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt Day of</hi> Auguſt, <hi>which ſhall be in the Year of our Lord God One Thouſand Six Hundred Forty and One, award, impoſe, or inflict any pain, penalty, fine, amerciament, impriſonment, or other Corporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon any of the Kings Subjects, for any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Misdemeanour, Crime, Offence, matter or thing whatſoever belonging to Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance or Iurisdiction, or ſhall</hi> Ex Officio, <hi>or at the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or Promotion of any Perſon whatſoever Vrge, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, tender, give or Miniſter unto any Church-warden, Sideman, or other Perſon whatſoever, any corporal Oath whereby he or ſhe ſhall or may be Charged or Oblieged to make any preſentment of any Crime or Offence, or to confeſs or accuſe himſelf or her ſelf of any Crime, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, Delinquency or Misdemeanour, or any neglect, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or thing whereby or by reaſon whereof he or ſhe, ſhall or may be ſiable, or expoſed to any cenſure, pain, penalty, or Puniſhment whatſoever: upon pain and penaity that every perſon, who ſhall offend contrary to this Statute, ſhall forfeit and pay treble Dammages to every Perſon thereby grieved, and the Summ of One Hundred pounds, to him or them who ſhall firſt Demand and Sue for the ſame: VVhich ſaid Treble Dammages and Summ of One Hundred Pounds, ſhall and may be Demanded and Recovered by Action of Debt, Bill, or Plaint in any Court of Record, wherein no Priviledge, Eſſoin, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or VVager of Law ſhall be admitted or allowed to the Defendant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And be it further Enacted, That every Perſon who ſhall be once Convicted of any Act, or Offence Prohibited by this Statute, ſhall for ſuch Act or Offence be from and after ſuch Conviction, utterly diſſabled to be or continue in any Office or Imployment in any Courts of Iuſtice whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or to exerciſe or execute any Power, Authority or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction, by force of any Commisſion or Letters Patents of the King his Heirs or Succeſſors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And be it further Enacted, That from and after the firſt Day of</hi> Auguſt, <hi>no New Court ſhall be Erected, Ordained, or Appointed within this Realm of</hi> England, <hi>or Dominion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51917:18"/>of</hi> Wales <hi>which ſhall or may have the like Power, Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or Authority: as the ſaid High Commiſſion Court now hath or pretendeth to have, but that all and every ſuch Letters, Patents, Commiſſions and grants made or to be made by his Majeſty his Heirs or Succeſſors. And all Power and Authority granted or pretended, or mentioned to be granted thereby and all Acts, Sentences and Decrees to be made by Vertue or Culler thereof, ſhall be utterly void and of no effect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After the making of this Act all Juriſdiction of the Spiritual Courts, was wholly dain'd as appears plainly by the Statute. Thus it ſtood ſtill, 13 <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> Now in this Act of <hi>Car Primi,</hi> it muſt be obſerved that it meddles no farther with the Act of <hi>Eliz.</hi> then that one branch about Commiſſions, it meddles not with the Eccleſiaſtical power being in the Crown nor with the Statute, 8 <hi>Eliz.</hi> Nor any thing of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. or <hi>Henry</hi> 8. which muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>Thus then their power was wholly diſcontinued till the thirteenth of <hi>Charles 2d.</hi> And then coming into their Biſhopricks and great Eſtates, they thought it hard that they muſt have their Spiritual Swords tied, therefore all hands to work to get looſe, and ſo an Act is paſſed the 13 <hi>Charles 2d.</hi> For Repeal of part of the Act <hi>Car Primi.</hi> And now they thought all was ſure, but as it fell out this will do them no good at all neither, for the Act which was intended to Repeal this Act of the 16 of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt hath miſrecited it, and called it an Act made the 17 of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, not only in the Title but all along in the body of the Act, which is plain upon the Roll, though not in the Statute Books, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Act for Explanation of a Clauſe, contained in an Act of Parliament, made in the ſeventeenth year of the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> Intituled an Act of Repeal of a Branch of a Statute <hi>Primo Elizabethe,</hi> concerning Commiſſions for Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhereas in an Act of Parliament made in the ſeaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year of the late King</hi> Charles, <hi>Intituled an Act for Repeal of a branch of</hi> Primo Elizabethe <hi>concerning Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical it is (amongſt other things) enacted: That no Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Vicar Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral nor any Ordinary whatſoever, nor any other Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Iudge, Officer or Miniſter of Iuſtice, nor
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51917:19"/>any other perſon or perſons whatſoever exerciſing Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual or Eccleſiaſtical Power, Authority or Iuriſdiction by any Grant Licence or Commiſſion of the Kings Majeſty, his Heirs or Succeſſors, or by any Power or Authority derived from the King his Heirs or Succeſſors, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhall (from and after the firſt day of</hi> Auguſt, <hi>which then ſhould be in the year of our Lord God one thouſand ſix hundred forty one) Award, Impoſe, or Iuflict, any Pain, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Fine, Amerciament, Impriſonment or other Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhment upon any of the Kings Subjects, for any contempt, miſdemeaner, crime, offence, matter or thing whatſoever belonging to Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance or Iuriſdiction without ſome doubt hath been made, that all Ordinary power of coertion and proceedings in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical were taken away, whereby the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courſe of Iuſtice in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical hath been obſtructed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be it therefore Declared and Enacted by the Kings Moſt Excellent Majeſty, by and with the advice and conſent of the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the Authority thereof that neither the ſaid Act, nor any thing therein contained doth or ſhall take away any ordinary Power or Authority from any of the ſaid Archbiſhops, Biſhops or any other perſon or perſons named as aforeſaid, but that they and every of them exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction, may proceed, determine, ſentence, execute, and exerciſe all manner of Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction, and all cenſures and coertions appertaining <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> belonging to the ſame before the making of the Act before recited, in all cauſes and matters belonging to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction, according to the Kings Majeſties Eccleſiaſtical Laws uſed and practiſed within this Realm, in as ample manner and form as they did and might lawfully have done before the making of the ſaid Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid that the aforeſaid recited Act of</hi> Decimo Septimo Caroli, <hi>and all the matters and clauſes therein contained (except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what concerns the High Commiſſion Court, or the new Errection) ſhall be and is hereby Repealed, to all intent and purpoſes whatſoever; any thing clauſe or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the ſaid Act contained to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided always, and it is hereby Enacted, That neither this Act nor any thing herein contained, ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51917:19"/>or be conſtrued to revive or give force to the ſaid Branch of the ſaid Statute made in the ſaid Year of the Reign of the ſaid late Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>mentioned in the ſaid Act of Parliament, made in the ſaid Seventeenth Year of the Reign of the ſaid King</hi> Charles, <hi>but that the ſaid Branch of the ſaid Statute made in the ſaid Firſt year of the Reign of the ſaid Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>ſhall ſtand and be Repealed in ſuch ſort as if this Act had never been made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided alſo, and it is hereby further Enacted, That it ſhall not be Lawful for any Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, Vicar-General, Chancellor, Commiſſary, or any other Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Iudge, Officer or Miniſter, or any other perſon, having or exerciſing Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, to Tender or Adminiſter to any perſon whatſoever, the Oath, uſually called the Oath</hi> Ex Officio, <hi>or any other Oath, whereby ſuch perſon to whom the ſame is tendered or Adminiſtred, may be charged or compelled to confeſs, or accuſe, or to purge him or her ſelf of any criminal matter or thing, whereby he or ſhe may be liable to Cenſure or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: Any thing in this Statute, or any other Law, Cuſtome or Vſage heretofore to the Contrary hereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provided always, That this Act or any thing therein contained, ſhall not extend or be conſtrued to extend to give unto any Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, or any other Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Iudge, Officer, or other perſon or perſons aforeſaid, any Power or Authority to Exerciſe, Execute, Inflict, or Determine any Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or Coertion, which they might not by Law have done before the year of our Lord</hi> 1639, <hi>nor to abridge or diminiſh the Kings Majeſties Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical matters and affairs, nor to conform the Commons made in the year</hi> 1640, <hi>nor any of them, nor any other Eccleſiaſtical Laws or Cannons not formerly confirmed, allowed or enacted by Parliament, or by the Eſtabliſhed Laws of the land as they ſtood in the year of our Lord,</hi> 1639.</p>
            </q>
            <p>So that then it follows that except they can find ſuch an Act as this Repeals, which muſt be one of the 17 of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, this will not help them for they will not find that this in Law can repeal the Act made the 16 of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt. And what follows if they have acted all this while and had no legal power, let the world Judge what a fine
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51917:20"/>threed they have ſpun for themſelves, if either the King ſhall call them to account or any private man that hath been Excommunicated, but it will be objected that this may be remedied it being but a miſtake to which I anſwer it may be mended, but it muſt be in Parliament.</p>
            <p>But then it is objected, That this Act of the <hi>13th</hi> of this King intends them a power to hold Courts.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer is plain, very true it doth ſo, but it muſt be according to the Kings Majeſties Eccleſiaſtical Laws ſtill, and it muſt be from and under him, as by Law, and ſure the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes before is the Law they muſt walk by, until the ſame are truly and exactly Repealed.</p>
            <p>But for a further Anſwer, If they obſerve this Statute well, and allow it to be a miſtake, as I affirm it is, they are not at all the better for this of <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> as to their Eccleſiaſtical pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they now Act by, if there were no miſtake at all for this of <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> does not help them in the leaſt, for in the laſt <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph</hi> of this Statute of the <hi>13th</hi> of this King, it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>They ſhall have no more power than they had in the Year</hi> 1639.</p>
            <p>Then ſee what they had in 1639, it is moſt plain all the reſt of the Statutes were then in force againſt them both of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> and <hi>Edw. 6th.</hi> Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> Laws.</p>
            <p>For this very Sentence and Judgement in Parliament before recited, was but in 1610. And I do aver they had no other power then but what thoſe Laws gave them; thus I have done with matter of Fact, as it lies, I leave all Men to judge, and govern themſelves as they ſhall ſee occaſion, and would be glad my Error might be corrected by them, if in any thing I have miſquoted or miſrepreſented the Caſe, hopeing that a more judicious perſon will undertake to correct it in what way or Method he likes beſt.</p>
            <p>There are Two or Three ſeveral Objections which I have met with in this Affair, the Firſt is this, That the King per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it, and if any wrong be done by the Spiritual Courts, it is to him, and what hath any private perſon to do to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern himſelf therein.</p>
            <p>In that the King may paſs it by, 'tis true, but wrong may be done by theſe Courts to the Subject as well as to the King; and there may be Damage to a ſingle Perſon by theſe Courts by being Excommunicated, which cannot be to the King, and whoever ſuffers under that Burden hath cauſe enough to complain and ſeek their Remedy, tho' the King think fit to forgive the wrong done to himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51917:20"/>
            <p>The other Objection, is, That the Courſe of the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Courts hath been ſuch time out of mind, and no hurt comes to the Subject by their Courts, whether it be done by Commiſſion or not.</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, That I never yet heard of any Good ever did come from thoſe Courts, but many have been ruined and undone by them; And in the next place for their Cuſtome time out of mind, there is no ſuch thing, if Cuſtome ſhould prevail againſt Law, which it cannot be, for the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt time they can bring for this Cuſtome is but 1610 at the furtheſt time; and there are ſome perſons yet living, can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that time. But I believe it will be hard for them to prove that they exerciſed Eccleſiaſtical Power by their own Authority in any time in the Reign of King <hi>James;</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if they do they cannot make it a Law, for an evil Cuſtom againſt Law never yet made a Law, and for them to ſay Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome will carry it, the Highway-Man may as well plead the ſame for Robbery, and ſay, <hi>Oh Sir, I have been accuſtomed to Rob, tho' there be a Law againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another Objection which carries as little weight as the reſt, and that is the Opinion of the Judges in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> which ought to have the Anſwer that before is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that it was an Extra-Judicial Opinion, and given at ſuch a time, and by the ſame Judges that over-ruled the Plea of the Lord <hi>Hollis</hi> and <hi>Elliot,</hi> which was many Years after rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Therefore to Sum up all, the caſe lies thus, before the 20 of <hi>H.</hi> the 8. The Spiritual Juriſdiction and all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in <hi>England</hi> by the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, was by from and under the power and authority of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> and by there Cannon Law afterwards to the end of his Reign all that power was inveſted wholly in the King, and no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority belonged to them in any matters whatever, but what muſt be derived by from and under him.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. of Famous memory did by his honeſt and wiſe Councel, not only approve of what was dune in the Church affairs, in <hi>H.</hi> the <hi>8ths.</hi> time, but goes on furder and takes away the very form and mould of the Spiritual Courts, by making a Law that thoſe Courts ſhould not ſo much as beheld in their one name, but in the name of the King and all there Citations and Proſſes whatever was to be in the Kings name as in Judicial proceeding at Law, and the Biſhops name of the <hi>Dioſeſs</hi> to be at the bottom, as teſt to the writ and not as Lord <hi>Paramount,</hi> the Kings
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51917:21"/>authority: and by this Kings Law they were not to uſe any Seal to the Court, but with the Kings Arms in Graven, ſo it reſted in his time.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Mary</hi> ſhe came in <hi>Popiſhly</hi> affected, and by the help of Cardinal <hi>Poole</hi> Legate from <hi>Rome,</hi> prevails with her for the good of her Soul and Honour to the unholy Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to paſs an Act, called an Act of repeal to take away all thoſe Laws that abridged the Power and Supremacy of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> ſence the 20 year of <hi>H.</hi> the 8. And as ſome will have it this Law of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. muſt be meant to be one of thoſe, but what reaſon can be in Law given is not yet known for it is not perticularly Repealed as other Laws are in that Statute of Repeal and; then in the next place being not ſo perticularly, it is believed it could not be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed by that Act of Repeal, becauſe that in the very ſame Act it doth ſet fourth perticularly. all other Acts intended to be repealed, and not that. Then Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in her firſt year Repealed the Act of Repeal made in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, and reſtores all again, as was in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8ths.</hi> time, and <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. And declared particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly that all manner of Eccleſiaſtical power muſt be from, and under her, and by her Authority and none elſe, and more particularly to ſhew all the Church power, was then loſt without new power given by that Act, a Clauſe, is incerted in the ſaid Act that She and her Succeſſors ſhall give command under the great Seal of <hi>England</hi> to ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmiſſions, as ſhe pleaſed from time to time to hold Court Eccleſiaſtical and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>To the ſame effect it is again declared by the Statute made the <hi>8th</hi> of her Reign. And it is moſt certain, that by Vertue of the Clauſe in that Statute <hi>Primo Eliz.</hi> That gives power of granting Commiſſions to hold Spiritual Courts they did Act, and without it neither Queen or King could grant ſuch Commiſſions, nor they hold any Courts, without ſuch Commiſſions.</p>
            <p>Thus then it continued all the time of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and by ſuch Commiſſions they acted and no other Authority was known, nor from her time can they ſhew other Authority to impower them but on the contrary they will find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves leſſened.</p>
            <p>For in King <hi>Jame</hi>'s time they acted by the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and in full Parliament, in 1610, it was owned of all hands.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:51917:21"/>
            <p>In King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt's time the Spiritual Courts became a Burden to the Nation, ſo great that the people were not able to bear them although they did Act by ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, or at leaſt ought ſo to do which appears plain by the Statute, 16 <hi>Car Primi,</hi> which takes away all their whole power, and as a reaſon or means to take away their power; what do the Parliament do, why it is moſt clear both by the Title and Body of the Act, they tell you they muſt repeal that part of the Law of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> that gave power to grant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions for them to hold Spiritual Courts. Therefore the taking away and Repealing that Branch of the Statute of <hi>Eliz.</hi> that gives power to grant Commiſſions, it was taken for grant, then that they had no power at all. For no more of that Statute was Repealed is evident, then what related to the Comiſſions, they did not let them looſe to Act as before it was ſo far from that, that it appears they intended not to let them Act at all, neither under the King in his Name nor any otherways whatever then in this of <hi>Car. 2d.</hi> The Eccleſiaſtical perſons meant to Repeal the Act of <hi>Primo Car.</hi> But miſtook the year, ſo in truth they did nothing at all but they may be liable to be called to account, for all they have acted ever ſince nor can they Act with ſafety, till this Law be mended for Acts of Parliament muſt be punctually repealed, and exactly recited or elſe in Law it will not do.</p>
            <p>But if that had been well Repealed it is far ſhort of giving them any power, for it is only to take away the Clauſe, that was repealed about given Commiſſions to hold Courts but gives them no new power at all, it doth not tell them notwithſtanding the Laws of <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. The reſt of the Statutes of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the practice in King <hi>James</hi> time, that they ſhall hold Courts in their own Names, no, it is ſo far from that, that the Act ſaith expreſly they ſhall have no other power by this Act, or was it intended them, then what they had in 1639, now if they can ſhew that they had any power given them between the year 1610, to the year 1639. Then I ſay, they are right and may go on, if not, I appeal to all mankind what culler or pretence theſe men can have to hold Courts Spiritual at all, much leſs by their own Prerogative or in their own Names; which I take to be as unlawful, and as directly againſt the Kings Prerogative as any thing can be, For that ſince all power Spiritual and Temporal is by Law inveſted in the King,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51917:22"/>they may as well hold Courts again under the <hi>Popes</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and in his Name, as in their own Names, and it is a wonderful thing to conſider that theſe Churchmen who cry down all for <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> and tells the World at every turn they are Sedious and Diſloyal that do not obey the Kings Laws and ſay as they ſay, although ſometimes they ſay and do they know not what themſelves. And yet what <hi>Phanatick</hi> is there this day in <hi>England,</hi> does or ever did make ſo bold with the Kings Prerogative, as theſe high <hi>Churchmen,</hi> who in every of their Courts as they call them, and every proceſs they make, ſay in effect as the great <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Woolſey</hi> did, when in his ſplender and glory in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ego &amp; Rex meos.</hi> But I conſidering we are here diſcourſing of Proteſtant Churchmen, and knowing well their very Tongues are tipped with Loyalty. We muſt not therefore venture to ſay more or meddle further then to beg their Charitable opinion once to a Diſcenter both from their Courts, and Cannons.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
